export const SOCIALSTUDIESA2016 = [

{
id: "question1",
question: "1. In Abraham Maslow’s theory of needs, realization of the individual’s potential at the ultimate is",
A: "love and acceptance",
B: "self-actualization",
C: "self-esteem",
D: "physiological",
answer: "B. self-actualization",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question2",
question: "2. The sum total of a person’s perceptions, beliefs, qualities and behavior constitute his or her",
A: "attitude",
B: "conscience",
C: "development",
D: "self",
answer: "D. self",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question3",
question: "3. The most effective way of developing one’s capabilities is through",
A: "education, training and self-control",
B: "education, training and self-determination",
C: "guidance, counseling and self-discipline",
D: "guidance, counseling and self-reliance",
answer: "B. education, training and self-determination",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question4",
question: "4. Irresponsible adolescent sexual behaviour needs to be controlled through",
A: "family planning",
B: "marital stability training",
C: "physical education",
D: "reproductive health education",
answer: "D. reproductive health education",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question5",
question: "5. Which of the following factors does, not contribute to the increase in adolescent pregnancy?",
A: "Broken homes",
B: "Lust for marital possession",
C: "Poverty",
D: "sex education",
answer: "D. sex education",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question6",
question: "6. An adolescent who indulges in pre-marital sex risks",
A: "being an orphan at early age",
B: "being thrown out of school",
C: "facing police prosecution",
D: "losing employment",
answer: "B. being thrown out of school",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question7",
question: "7. Which of the following factors can be regarded as a threat to national integration effort?",
A: "Adoption of a common national language",
B: "Encouragement of ethnocentric",
C: "Encouragement of inter-ethnic marriages",
D: "Upholding the cultural values of the people",
answer: "B. Encouragement of ethnocentric",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question8",
question: "8. A cultural practice which clearly identifies each ethnic group in Ghana is",
A: "A code of dressing",
B: "family life",
C: "music and dance",
D: "system of inheritance",
answer: "C. music and dance",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question9",
question: "9. Marriages can best be sustained when there is",
A: "adequate financial resources",
B: "guidance and counseling",
C: "mutual respect, love and trust",
D: "regular communication",
answer: "C. mutual respect, love and trust",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question10",
question: "10. The arrangement where newly married couples live in their own household helps",
A: "limit family interference",
B: "prevent divorce",
C: "prevent domestic violence",
D: "promote an unending love",
answer: "A. limit family interference",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question11",
question: "11. A family composed of a couple and their immediate offspring is referred to as",
A: "extended family",
B: "external family",
C: "nuclear family",
D: "composite family",
answer: "C. nuclear family",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question12",
question: "12. The system of inheritance in the Ghanaian traditional society is relevant because it",
A: "ensures stability of marriage",
B: "protects external family property",
C: "preserves cultural identity",
D: "promotes continuity of procreation",
answer: "A. ensures stability of marriage",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question13",
question: "13. Parenthood refers to a man or woman who",
A: "cares for a younger child",
B: "cares for his or her biological child",
C: "influence of the mass media",
D: "works at a nursery school",
answer: "B. cares for his or her biological child",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question14",
question: "14. Flouting the authority of parents can result from",
A: "constant scolding of the child",
B: "hereditary traits of the child",
C: "influence of the mass media",
D: "regular parental control",
answer: "A. constant scolding of the child",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question15",
question: "15. Socialization basically helps the individual to",
A: "adjust to his or her environment",
B: "acquire academic certificate",
C: "have access to higher education",
D: "obtain a well-paid job",
answer: "A. adjust to his or her environment",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question16",
question: "16. The basic requirement for living harmoniously in a community is to",
A: "develop the spirit of co-existence",
B: "have many good friends",
C: "obtain formal education",
D: "participate fully in communal labour",
answer: "A. develop the spirit of co-existence",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question17",
question: "17. An activity that does not contribute to deforestation is the",
A: "construction of roads",
B: "expansion of settlements",
C: "mining of minerals",
D: "promotion of agro forestry",
answer: "D. promotion of agro forestry",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question18",
question: "18. The major cause of global warming is",
A: "fire outbreaks in market places all over the world",
B: "polluting the sea with waste materials from industries",
C: "the burning of bushes in preparation for agricultural production",
D: "the burning of fossil fuel such as coal, oil and natural gas",
answer: "D. the burning of fossil fuel such as coal, oil and natural gas",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question19",
question: "19. Education can bring about change in the Ghanaian society if it is structured to meet the needs of the",
A: "educated elite",
B: "family",
C: "people",
D: "private businesses",
answer: "C. people",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question20",
question: "20. Self-reliance for economic growth in a country calls for the development of",
A: "democratic governance",
B: "human resources",
C: "import trade",
D: "natural resources",
answer: "B. human resources",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question21",
question: "21. Peace building is mainly aimed at creating",
A: "a forum for national integration",
B: "equity in society",
C: "freedom and justice",
D: "harmonious living in society",
answer: "D. harmonious living in society",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question22",
question: "22. Which of the following factors is not a source of conflict in a society?",
A: "discrimination",
B: "Greed",
C: "Suspicion",
D: "Tolerance",
answer: "D. Tolerance",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question23",
question: "23. A leader and a follower are inseparable mainly because, the",
A: "follower accepts responsibility from the leader",
B: "follower accepts to be guided by the leader",
C: "leader and the follower are partners in development",
D: "leader has the authority to guide the follower",
answer: "C. leader and the follower are partners in development",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question24",
question: "24. Democratic leadership style is widely accepted at work places because it",
A: "brings about competition among workers",
B: "encourages worker participation in decision-making",
C: "ensures dependency of followers on the leader",
D: "sacrifices quality for greater work",
answer: "B. encourages worker participation in decision-making",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question25",
question: "25. To achieve the goals and aspirations of a group, the leader must have",
A: "an attractive personality",
B: "support from the youth",
C: "vision and foresight",
D: "wealth and respect",
answer: "C. vision and foresight",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question26",
question: "26. The distribution of power among the institutions of government is known as",
A: "balance of power",
B: "checks and balances",
C: "separation of powers",
D: "rule of law",
answer: "C. separation of powers",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question27",
question: "27. Checks and balances are important in a democratic system of government because it",
A: "discourages dictatorial rule",
B: "grants absolute freedom to the electorate",
C: "helps opposition parties win elections",
D: "curtails individual’s right and freedoms",
answer: "A. discourages dictatorial rule",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question28",
question: "28. Which of the following options is not a feature of democratic governance?",
A: "Constitution",
B: "Decree",
C: "Human rights",
D: "Rule of law",
answer: "B. Decree",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question29",
question: "29. The fundamental human rights of a citizen may be restricted when",
A: "a person is taken to court",
B: "the executive unilaterally decides so",
C: "there is a state anniversary",
D: "there is a state of emergency",
answer: "D. there is a state of emergency",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question30",
question: "30. One right which is not extended to foreigners in Ghana is",
A: "expression of personal views",
B: "open trial in a law court",
C: "possession of personal property",
D: "there is a state of emergency",
answer: "D. there is a state of emergency",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question31",
question: "31. One problem confronting the Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS) is",
A: "insufficient capital within the sub-region",
B: "the absence of an African High command",
C: "the periodic election of its chairperson",
D: "the poor weather conditions in the sub-region",
answer: "A. insufficient capital within the sub-region",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question32",
question: "32. One objective for the New Partnership for Africa’s Development (NEPAD) is to",
A: "empower women in Africa",
B: "eradicate colonialism",
C: "quicken economic integration",
D: "remove trade barriers",
answer: "A. empower women in Africa",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question33",
question: "33. The most reliable avenue for the youth to get employment is",
A: "acquisition of skills",
B: "consulting the internet for vacancies",
C: "making personal contacts",
D: "searching for newspaper advertisements",
answer: "A. acquisition of skills",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question34",
question: "34. In Ghana, the contribution of the youth to national development is minimal because they",
A: "are marginalized",
B: "do not have sufficient capital",
C: "lack self-confidence",
D: "lack the right orientation and exposure",
answer: "D. lack the right orientation and exposure",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question35",
question: "35. Scientific knowledge is based on",
A: "one’s ingenuity",
B: "religious beliefs",
C: "tested facts",
D: "traditional beliefs",
answer: "C. tested facts",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question36",
question: "36. Scientific and technological knowledge is acquired to solve human problems through",
A: "availability of natural resources",
B: "establishment of grammar schools",
C: "ingenuity and creativity",
D: "stability and unity",
answer: "C. ingenuity and creativity",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question37",
question: "37. The natural resources of a country can benefit its people only when they are",
A: "given necessary publicity",
B: "kept for future generation",
C: "properly exploited",
D: "renewable",
answer: "C. properly exploited",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question38",
question: "38. To ensure efficient use of human resource in Ghana, the government should",
A: "appoint only members of the ruling party to occupy positions",
B: "appoint only qualified people to occupy positions",
C: "pay higher wages and salaries to workers",
D: "redeploy more civil servants to the rural areas",
answer: "B. appoint only qualified people to occupy positions",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question39",
question: "39. The improvement in the standard of living of people in a given area as a result of positive attitudinal change is described as",
A: "community development",
B: "national development",
C: "self-actualization",
D: "social development",
answer: "D. social development",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question40",
question: "40. The most appropriate way to increase food production in Ghana is to",
A: "award prices to national best farmers",
B: "establish state farms to absorb the unemployed",
C: "make credits and inputs readily available",
D: "recruit more people into the agricultural sector",
answer: "C. make credits and inputs readily available",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question41",
question: "41. The main goal of national development is to",
A: "ensure good governance",
B: "create job opportunities",
C: "expand the export base of the country",
D: "raise the standard of living of the people",
answer: "D. raise the standard of living of the people",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question42",
question: "42. A large proportion of the labour force in West Africa is employed in the",
A: "industrial section",
B: "primary sector",
C: "secondary sector",
D: "tertiary sector",
answer: "B. primary sector",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question43",
question: "43. One outstanding feature of a buoyant economy is",
A: "borrowing without collateral security",
B: "easy access to foreign loans",
C: "high per capital income",
D: "lending with security",
answer: "C. high per capital income",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question44",
question: "44. For individuals to ensure their sustainability in life, they need to",
A: "acquire quality education and training",
B: "save all their incomes in a bank",
C: "seek employment in the public sector",
D: "register with an insurance company",
answer: "A. acquire quality education and training",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question45",
question: "45. Ghana can sustain her growth and development through the following ways except",
A: "education and training of her citizens",
B: "development of maintenance culture",
C: "regular inspection of public property",
D: "spending more money on new projects",
answer: "D. spending more money on new projects",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question46",
question: "46. Efficiency of labour in Ghana is mainly influenced by",
A: "education and training",
B: "government policies",
C: "the size of available land",
D: "the size of the work force",
answer: "A. education and training",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question47",
question: "47. One obstacle of family planning in Ghana is",
A: "puberty rites",
B: "naming ceremonies",
C: "old age",
D: "religious beliefs",
answer: "D. religious beliefs",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question48",
question: "48. Which of the following factors will not impede the smooth of population census in Ghana?",
A: "Inadequate number of qualified enumerators",
B: "Inadequate provision of logistics",
C: "Inaccessibility of remote cars",
D: "Non-availability of electricity",
answer: "D. Non-availability of electricity",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question49",
question: "49. A person who uses available resources and skills to produce goods and services is referred to as",
A: "a businessman",
B: "an entrepreneur",
C: "a producer",
D: "a retailer",
answer: "B. an entrepreneur",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question50",
question: "50. Productivity can be reduced by the following factors except",
A: "inappropriate technology",
B: "low dependency",
C: "low quality workforce",
D: "poor condition of service",
answer: "B. low dependency",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},


]